<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>imported on David Davó's dev log</title><link>https://blog.ddavo.me/tags/imported/</link><description>Recent content in imported on David Davó's dev log</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>David Davó (c) 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 11:50:13 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.ddavo.me/tags/imported/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Just Get My Data: Get your data from various web services</title><link>https://blog.ddavo.me/posts/projects/jgmd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 11:50:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.ddavo.me/posts/projects/jgmd/</guid><description>We all know that since the last couple of years we can ask any web that services EU citizens to delete our data, but&amp;hellip; we can also ask them to send us our data, in a legible format.
To prevent us from exerting our rights, a lot of sites use dark patterns, tricks that make you do things that you didn&amp;rsquo;t mean to, so you give up before finishing your task.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We all know that since the last couple of years we can ask any web that services EU citizens to delete our data, but&hellip; <strong>we can also ask them to send us our data, in a legible format.</strong></p>
<p>To prevent us from exerting our rights, a lot of sites use <a href="https://darkpatterns.org/">dark patterns</a>, tricks that make you do things that you didn&rsquo;t mean to, so you give up before finishing your task. An aggressive design that can frustrate users and makes us scream against the screen: &ldquo;I DON&rsquo;T WANT MY DATA ANY MORE!!&rdquo;</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s why <a href="https://justgetmydata.com/es">Just Get My Data</a> was created. It&rsquo;s a directory of direct links, with notes and mini-tutorials to make it easier to get your data. There are a lot of services, and you can sort, search and filter them (by difficulty, for example).</p>
<p>For example, Apple, Coinbase, LinkedIn and Google have a green, easy difficulty level. This means that they have set up an automatized and easy to follow process to exercise your GDPR rights. On the other hand, platforms like Twitch have a red, difficult colour, as you have to follow a manual process, sending them e-mails in English (which can be a problem if it&rsquo;s not your main language), giving them more personal data, telling them why you want your data, and finding the One Ring.</p>
<p>This <em>semaphore</em> system allows us to call-out companies and, maybe some CEO doesn&rsquo;t like to have their company listed in red.</p>
<p>JustGetMyData is a fork of <a href="https://justdeleteme.xyz/">JustDeleteMe</a>, a web that helps you similarly to delete your account from online services sorting out dark patterns.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s free software, so you can help too if you want. A lot of people helped translate the page to multiple languages, or new entries on how to get your data from a service. If you want to participate developing Just Get My Data, you can do so on <a href="https://github.com/justgetmydata/jgmd">GitHub</a>, we are happy to receive any help!</p>
<p>Did you know all your rights? Or did you just know about the right to delete your data?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>